- Good afternoon Hong Kong.
I hope you're guys doing well.
Very excited to be here with you all
to talk about really the latest with Solana
on this exciting little session we're gonna have
on the really building the rules internet markets.
My name is Henry Arcelin, I'm the co-founder
of Nine Blocks Capital.
One of the market neutral crypto hedge funds
regulated in Dubai and spent 15 years here in Hong Kong.
So good to be back here, back home,
actually on that perspective.
We're gonna talk today about a lot of the latest developments
on Solana, what's happening in the ecosystem
and the future of Solana.
And to do this, we're joined by Lily Liu,
the president of the Solana Foundation.
Lily, great, welcome to Hong Kong as well.
- Thank you, Henry.
- Fun fact by the way, Lily, many people know her
as the president of the Solana Foundation.
One thing you may not know about her,
she used to be in the crew team at Stanford
in the rowing activity, in the rowing sports,
the boats of eight people from what I understand.
Hong Kong, we are dragging boats.
Here we go, and you have rowing as well in crew.
- And it's very relevant to crypto
because what it teaches you is pain tolerance.
- Pain tolerance and unfortunately,
well, we need that a lot in the industry.
So Lily, there's a lot of, I'm sure a lot of people
want to hear from you on what's happening
in the Solana ecosystem.
I want to cover a lot of developments
on the Solana on broader markets as well.
But maybe me to set the scene.
Can you be shared with our audience?
What is some of the latest developments
you're seeing with the Solana ecosystem
and then we'll dive right in?
- Well, frankly, everything is happening on Solana, right?
If you look at every single sector, at some point,
people have called Solana, the DeFi chain,
the NFT chain, the gaming chain,
the deep pin chain, the stable coin chain,
and lately, yes, the meme coin chain.
And so what it really means to be a general purpose L1
is that you have to do the hard thing,
which is that you have to have breadth and depth
across a full variety of different use cases
and verticals that exist in this kind of ever-growing industry.
- But you don't think, I mean, you mentioned meme coins,
actually, don't you bring, they bring a lot of new users.
I mean, from a data perspective,
a lot of the users must be coming
from the meme coin ecosystem, I presume, right?
- They do, well, it's no secret that, what,
16 years on from when Bitcoin was created,
what is the ever-present critique
that a lot of people have had of this industry?
That it's all just about speculation.
And that it's been, you know, initially Bitcoin was,
2013 was when it got up to like 1,300,
and people felt a certain way about that.
And I'm sure you guys remember the ICO days
when denta coin was worth a couple of billion dollars,
and then there was, of course, the NFT cycle,
gaming coin, so on and so forth.
So, the idea that people want to be able to speculate
on stuff on chain is not new.
- Yeah, so why do you see the future?
You know, Lily, let's say we look a couple years
down the line, the last today, today,
we've had numerous conversations on various L1s
and how the ecosystem is growing.
What's your view, let's say, not only from a Solana perspective,
but also yours on the future of like a cross-chain
and multi L1 ecosystem?
Do you believe they'll be interoperability?
Do you believe they'll be 50 L1s?
Like, how do you see the future roadmap?
- Sure, I think there's gonna be,
I don't think you're gonna have the same market,
kind of dominance allocation as you have,
and for example, search or in e-commerce.
Because I think that the cost to go start market
and get to some degree of scale on a new chain
is that startup cost and also the incentive to exit
is just a fundamentally different kind of
expected value calculation than if you're building
in the web to world, whether it's e-commerce SaaS
or whatever it might be, right?
And you know, even as those kind of EV calculations
come down over time, as there's more chains
and more use case and so on and so forth built out,
I think that's one of the kind of,
one of many unique dynamics in crypto,
which is that it's open source.
Anyone, almost anyone can go and launch a chain.
That does not mean that all chains in the same way
that not all websites are equivalent, right?
There's, I don't even know how many millions of websites
and yet there are a few that are hugely dominant.
So I think yes, it's gonna be a multi-chain world
and also what we've seen is that
because these chains are not just technology,
there are also communities
and there are also communities of users
and that is actually what gives coins
and chains longevity over time.
And so essentially once a coin has a community,
they don't really actually go away.
I mean, if you, I don't know how many people
have looked at the market cap of, for example,
Ethereum Classic, which very few people talk about,
or even Bitcoin Gold or Bitcoin Diamond,
and they have huge market caps still
because of sort of the original size of the community
they were imbued with and also longevity as well.
So I think yes, it's gonna be a multi-chain ecosystem
and recognize that, but you know,
what I think is going to be the most unique
about something like Solana is what really drives value,
why are blockchains valuable?
Well, I think that it's always been,
blockchains have always been about
creating global financial infrastructure, right?
That is the title of the white paper.
It says peer-to-peer electronic cash system.
It does not say digital gold,
which is not to say that, you know,
that there's a store of value
that's extremely important for us to kind of,
for that to be basically the anchor asset
of our entire industry.
But what about the rest of that vision, right?
Who's gonna be building that
and what infrastructure can support that?
So that from my perspective is what Solana is here to do.
That's why we talk about internet capital markets,
being the infrastructure for that.
But when you look in the future of Solana,
I mean, obviously we're talking about the world internet markets,
but do you believe each chain will have a specialization
or an area they're mostly focused on?
If for Solana, what do you think that niche will be,
if any?
Well, I wouldn't frame it as a niche.
I think that if the whole purpose of blockchains
is to be global financial infrastructure,
then inherently this entire kind of tech stack,
this entire purpose of this industry
is about creating a financial layer,
a financial infrastructure,
which is accessible to five and a half billion people, right?
The quantum of people that have access to the internet.
And if that's the case,
then really the core function is to have liquidity, right?
To provide global liquidity.
And one could look at the kind of extreme sort of explosion
of interest in speculative use cases
and say what that proves out
is that if you can tap into the global liquidity
of anyone who can log onto the internet,
then you have potential explosive markets.
And so I think, I don't see that as actually as a niche.
I see that as being the foundational purpose
of what we're all doing here.
Yeah, it's broader than that.
You know, I remember when post FTX,
a lot of people said, "Oh, Solana is dead.
There's not much interest."
And obviously Solana has had a great,
obviously had rocket, choppy couple of months,
but I mean, it's been actually quite a successful year
or two since FTX, especially to what you attribute
the success of Solana.
Is it the power of the community?
Is it the tech?
Is it the foundation of a good, great job?
Like, what do we draw a lot of this at this certain interest?
It's really the tech in the community.
And from the outside observer in November 22 and December 22,
I can understand why a lot of people looked at Solana
and said most certainly dead, right?
Most certainly roadkill might come up for a breath or two,
but that's done.
But really from the perspective of being inside the community,
not much changed, right?
People were still building
and still had actually doubled down in conviction.
And not even that.
I will say there were a number of people
that in November 22 actually said,
"I feel excited about this," right?
Because we have a chance to continue building
what we believe in and really rebuild the ecosystem as well.
So maybe it's just the pain tolerance, right?
We talked about it earlier.
- Exactly.
Rowan comes in, being crew comes in handy.
Any interest, any regions of the world
where you're seeing more interest on Solana
that compare like globally
when you guys look at it from a global perspective?
- Yeah, so Solana, look, open source,
ultimately you're just going to have repo.
We're all public servants of a GitHub repo
is what we all are at the end of the day.
So this technology, open source is inherently global.
That said, it's something that should be,
should feel Chinese and China,
should feel American and America,
should feel German and Germany and Indian and India, right?
So the use cases and what people want to do
with the underlying technology will be expressed
in the developer community, in the application layer,
and the choices that people make,
and that's exactly what it should be.
Now, if you ask me, what are the,
what are the most important markets in crypto?
Well, it's always been the same answer, right?
Which are the two large markets
that have breath in talent and in capital?
Well, that's the US and China.
And over the last four years,
I wouldn't say that both of those markets
have been terribly open to crypto.
That's where everything has started
from the very beginning.
So it's kind of like an ebb and flow type of thing.
I think since November, when we have a just total sea change,
and it kind of like that US-shaped hole
in the middle of this industry is now being filled,
did a complete 180, I think we're going to see
a ton of changes, right?
Because what's happening is the US is just changing
the overton window on every topic, right?
Way outside of crypto as well,
but also changing kind of where the median point is
on crypto regulation, wanting to be a leader in technology,
and also seeing stablecoins as being strategic to the US.
And I think that's going to really push
quite a number of people around the world.
To what extent are from a scale to one to 10?
Of course, we all know that obviously changing the US
is positive for the industry,
and we all see what's happened, different conversation
from stablecoins to strategic reserve discussions
to the end of regulation by enforcement as well.
In which, what is the main development you are watching
in the US, you think will have an outsized impact
on not only on the Solana,
but also the broader crypto ecosystem?
- Yes, I think that certainly there's going to be
a lot of kind of legislation and very specific things
that people are looking at, right?
But the biggest one that already has been signaled
is we're no longer going to persecute
the crypto industry, right?
And we're no longer going to take this entire group
of people just as a class,
because of some sort of ideological disagreement,
and we're going to say they're all bad,
and they should all should be debunked,
and in indirect ways, take the full weight of the state,
and turn that against this industry.
Okay, great, so we're over that.
And then I think we'll see what gets embraced,
but I think one that is very aligned
is on stable points.
And so from the US perspective, it's very clear
that the US wants to be dominant in all technologies
that matter, and the US is also very interested
in extending US dollar dominance,
and stable points are a way of continuing extend
the economic sphere of the dollar.
I was looking at some charts the other day,
and there are 50 economies around the world
that have over 5% CPI inflation, right?
And that accounts for about 1 billion people in the world.
And so I think the US just sees this very strategically,
and potentially even that incremental demand,
perhaps even being able to affect long-term interest rates,
which is a big KPI of the treasury at the moment.
- Yeah, I can imagine that.
You know, one topic that I'm sure you've been asked
is multiple times.
Many people think about Solana,
they think about meme coins,
and now the last 72 hours,
we think about Libra with the whole debacle there.
To what extent do you believe this whole meme coin,
Libra, let's say noise around, pumped up fun,
and everything was positive or negative
on the brother Solana ecosystem?
- Well, I don't think that Libra is bad for everyone, right?
I don't think there's any question about that.
- You don't think it's bad or it's not?
- I think it is bad for everyone.
- It's bad, yeah, okay.
- Right, it's very clearly bad for everyone involved.
I think that's a pretty terrible situation.
I don't think there's much to discuss there.
I think that, now with meme coins,
okay, well, that's anywhere between 20 and 50,000
meme coins a day, are all of them Libra?
No, are all of them going to be sort of retirement assets
you're gonna be holding down,
handing down to your children?
- What, you're not?
- No, but what I think,
you know, I go back to regulation again and again,
but what's happened in this industry is,
so there's this technology that sort of remixes
money, social connections, a sense of community,
and does that globally?
It's a pretty radical technology at the end of the day.
And has the ability to kind of also recombine aspects
of what you would previously have called
a transaction token, utility token,
and also things that have some sort of yield bearing element
to them.
And so because of this kind of regulatory uncertainty,
we've had basically all jurisdictions in the world,
what people have been pushed into,
is they've been pushed into the extremes.
They've been pushed into, well, anything I do that I sort of,
well, if I engage in sort of good faith innovation
around governance mechanisms,
on-chain crisis governing mechanisms,
ways of sort of actually transparently engaging
the community in utility governance, whatever,
that's a really risk area to be in.
Or even if you have a token that represents a share,
let's call it a fee pool, that's also considered.
So everything that is, that even has a little bit of
something in the middle is, well, you better not do that.
Otherwise, you basically spend all of your money on lawyers.
So let's push this entire industry to do things
where people just throw out their hands
at the very beginning and say, I told you it's worth nothing,
never will be worth anything.
And I think that that's actually been the product
of the regulatory environment in which we live.
What I think would be a lot more interesting
is to explore all of the, you call them structure products
in between, right?
And the ability to have a token that entitles you to,
for example, some of the fee revenue
in some of these protocols, right?
That is, that's always been part of the roadmap
of, for example, DeFi, but no one has dared to do that
because of just the thicket of, you name it,
that would just encounter you on day one.
- It's very ironic, because it's very ironic.
In a way, regulators, they put the constraints are so hard
that it pushes people on the sidelines, right?
And that's what obviously is a lot of interest.
Or, I mean, you could argue for a lot of people
that are completely cut off of the system,
meme comments are becoming the way.
When it comes to DeFi, actually, do you believe,
I presume you're pretty bullish on the future of DeFi,
what, any vertical of DeFi you think is very exciting,
and especially from a Solana perspective?
- Well, we talk about PayPal a lot.
- Yep.
- And so to date, DeFi has always been synonymous with trading.
The core transaction is a trade of one token
for another token, but the original vision for the space
is the peer-to-peer electronic cash system.
That's a transactional economy.
It's fundamentally a payments economy
where you're sending in, let's call it a token,
for a good or a service in return.
Where is that economy?
Why does that not exist on chain?
Now, might not be surprised that my answer to that
is that it has not been able to exist on chain
because we haven't had performant infrastructure, okay, right?
You would expect that would be my answer.
But I think that that is the part of,
if you think about DeFi more broadly than trading,
like truly decentralized finance,
like an economy that exists on chain
on this kind of global financial infrastructure,
then I would say payments is that huge,
that's kind of like our white whales in industry.
And that's what I'm the most excited about.
- Well, last question before we move
to the fire round of questions.
You obviously run the foundation
of one of the biggest L ones right now globally.
What is the biggest challenge of running a foundation?
It's a very unique role you have.
- Maybe just the time zones, right?
(laughing)
There's always someone who wants to talk to you.
So I think that the sheer breadth of what is happening.
So if you think about the range of on web two,
just think about the range of people who use the internet
and the range of use cases
and even just content that exists on the internet.
Now, at least on the internet,
there's like no one to call like 1-800-TCPIP doesn't exist.
Whereas that's the same case of what happens
within Solana, there's a full range of financial content.
And so on one end, you'll have the money market fund,
which is like and unobjectable to everyone.
And then on the other end, in the current world,
you have financial content
that a lot of people find to be very controversial.
Let's call them meme points, right?
And so that whole, then you can imagine
kind of like, let's just call it the breadth
of humanity and civilization that spans
those two ends of the spectrum.
And so I think finding ways to be relevant to that full range,
because I think that's what it means
to be global financial infrastructure, right?
That's what it means to be this open source protocol
that you do need to be accessible, available
and infrastructure for the full range of assets,
but it's also the full range of humanity.
- The full range of humanity, I love it.
So Lily, we have literally less than two minutes left.
My bell is with me back in Hong Kong.
I'm gonna ask you quick questions
and I want one or two words answers.
- Okay. - You ready?
- Mm-hmm.
- You're back in Hong Kong.
What's your favorite thing in Hong Kong?
- Eating.
- Food.
- The food, here we go.
(bell rings)
If, whoa, even the sheet is falling.
Lily, if you were not in the crypto industry,
what other industry would you be in?
- Being a tiger mom.
- A tiger mom, here we go.
As a tiger mom, what is the one course
you think kids should go learn right now
that you wish you had learned when you were a kid?
- Oh, well, all starts and ends with math.
- Math, here we go.
(bell rings)
That's a favorite in Hong Kong.
- Very predictable, yes.
- This is a tricky one.
If you could hold one other coin, non-sulana,
for the next 10 years, I'm not allowed to sell.
What would you hold?
(bell rings)
- Obviously Bitcoin.
- Bitcoin.
(bell rings)
- Order's coin.
(laughs)
If you could go back to university today
and take one course you wish at taking,
what course would you take?
- I would have taken many fewer classes
in Hong Kong at more with my friends.
- Here we go.
(bell rings)
Interesting one.
Donald Trump gives you a call
and wants to put you on their crypto committee.
What's the one advice you give to Donald Trump?
- Move faster.
Here we go.
What is the one other layer one you admire,
you think have done a good job
with your community building and their foundation?
- I think Ethereum has done an incredible job
of community building, they led the way.
- Ethereum, here we go.
Another tricky one.
Tomorrow morning you have to go launch
and you start up.
You have the choice of these following co-founders.
Jackma, Jeff Bezos, Elon Musk, or Taylor Swift.
- I'll tell you which one it is.
- Who do you pick?
(laughs)
- Check any of the first three.
- So Taylor Swift.
- Uh, probably not.
- No, I was like, yeah, yeah, one of the first three.
(bell rings)
Interesting one now.
This is the final question.
Question anybody comes on stage with me
or goes onto my TV show.
Lily, yeah, you have a chance to have dinner,
lunch or dinner with one person that are alive.
Lunch or dinner with one person that are alive.
Who would you have lunch or dinner with?
- I don't have to have lunch or dinner with Trump.
- What?
- Trump.
- Trump, here we go.
Guys, this is Lily Liu, the president of Solana Foundation.
Thank you very much for being with us today.
We'll pass it back to our MC.
Thank you very much, everybody.
(upbeat music)